[Music]
Stanford
University so let's
begin I'm going to review very quickly I
hope
quickly we described a simple system
consisting of one cubit I'm going to
change my terminology a little bit I'm
going to start calling that Cubit a
spin don't worry about what it has to do
with spinning at the moment of course
more important is that it's a little
point now I use the term
pointer I began to use the word pointer
to refer to vectors in three-dimensional
space while I was writing I realized
that that's awfully awkward and um
unfamiliar terminology and I decided to
replace it with another term the the
standard term three vectors vectors in
three-dimensional space I may sometimes
use the term pointer but I think I'm
more likely to speak of three vectors
and a three Vector means a vector in
real space the more General concept when
I when I simply say Vector more likely
I'm speaking about the abstract notion
of a vector space and the elements of a
vector
space just uh to warn you and keep the
language uh
clear now we talked about this Cubit
which is now become a
spin it has some of the character of
being a little three Vector in space
there is some sense or other in which it
points in a direction and that we can
confirm by an
experiment uh as was said before once we
start thinking about quantum mechanics
we really do have to think
about systems and their connection with
apparat apparati is that a word apparati
I'm not sure
apparatuses apparatuses I'm not sure
what the plural apparat anybody know the
app the plural of apparatus apparatus oh
just
apparatus okay just apparatus um we do
have to think about the connection with
their
apparatuses that measure
them and we don't get away with just
ignoring it what what's the difference
first of all I'll tell you what the
basic differences in classical physics
and Quantum quantum physics in classical
physics measurements can be arbitrarily
gentle arbitrarily gentle means that you
can find out anything that you want
about a system in principle by
interacting with it with something that
changes anything about it by an
arbitrarily small
amount for example you want to locate
the location of a particle in classical
physics how do you do it you shine some
light on it you shine some light on it
and you make an
image of course you have to use light
which is small enough wavelength that it
can resolve the the object this is true
but there's no limit to
how weak a light signal can be at a
given wavelength you can make the light
signal as weak as you like so that it
carries as little energy as you
like as little momentum as you like let
it interact with the thing you're
interested in form an image and then
after that image has been formed it can
be magnified not magnified in the sense
of making it bigger but what's the right
word for uh Amplified it can be
Amplified and so the experiment itself
can be arbitrarily gentle and still find
out anything you might want to know
about the system the result of that is
an experiment can always be done which
has no effect whatever
on future experiments on subsequent
experiments done for example right
afterwards that's classical physics
quantum physics is not like that quantum
physics is such that experiments
inevitably change
systems any experiment to measure
something will change something else
it's almost as though the experiment to
measure coins was such that every time I
looked looked at the coin the coin
jumped up in the air and uh and uh
randomly flipped itself we know that
doesn't happen and we can measure the
state of the coin gently without
changing
it quantum mechanics not so clear not
well it is clear it's clear that that
cannot be done okay but let's uh we're
going to talk a little bit before we
move on to more about Vector spaces and
operators and the mathematics of uh
quantum theory I want to talk a little
more about the logic of it and in what
way logic in quantum mechanics is
different than logic In classical
physics uh let's go back to our Spin and
our
apparatus the spin is
a I'll draw it as a little arrow whether
it truly corresponds to anything that
looks like a classical Arrow or not is
irrelevant we have to draw it on the
Blackboard and anything I draw on the
Blackboard will be
classical uh just because ink and pens
are classical or approximately classical
and an apparatus the apparatus is a
window that uh that has a number that
comes out of it number appears in the
window tells you the result of the
experiment and it also happens to have a
direction in it which tells you which
side which side is up how to orient it
uh in fact it might have a whole set of
three axes that tell you how to orient
it but that's not important just the up
Axis is what's
important and when the apparatus is
pointing up the only in fact no matter
what direction the apparatus is pointing
in when it interacts with the spin it
produces a number in the window and that
number in the window is either + one or
minus one no matter what direction the
apparatus is pointing in and no matter
what has happened to the spin
beforehand when the apparatus is
pointing up we will say that what it has
measured is the Z component of spin
let's put some axes in here Z up x to
the right and Y out of the
Blackboard and when the apparatus is
pointing up we'll say that it produces
an experimental experimental number
which measures the Z component of the
spin now is that particularly
interesting to think of it as having a
directionality when we say it's a z
component of the spin we're imagining
that this object here has a sense of
direction ality to it how can we test if
it has a direction a sense of
directionality to it well we can prepare
the spin in a state of what we think is
pointing up by simply letting it
interact with the apparatus and when the
apparatus appears with a plus one sign
in it we'll say ahuh the spin is up if
we do it again with the same apparatus
pointing in the same direction with the
same spin we'll get up up again and up
again and up again in that sense quantum
mechanics allows for reproducible
experiments if you measure the same
thing several times in a row with the
same
apparatus you will get the same answer
over and over so things are not that
weird and that's awfully important
because we have to have some concept of
reproducibility of experimental results
in order to make any sense out of things
so this is a good thing when you measure
something and you measure it again and
again and again you get the same answer
yeah so how does that fit in with what
you just said that we're going to come
to it we're going to come to it we're
going to come to it well I didn't say
that experiments are necessarily so
ungentle that when you measure anything
you affect everything the answer is you
affect some things in this case when you
measure something you don't affect that
same thing if you measure it again the
same thing again you'll get the same
answer okay now you could then say all
now that I have detected that the spin
is up let me turn the the uh the
apparatus completely over and point
down If This Were a
thermometer measuring the temperature I
don't think we would expect it to
measure minus the temperature if we
turned it over right no not not not if
it was any kind of decent
thermometer so we would therefore to say
that the the temperature does not have a
sense of orientation certainly not in
this Sense on the other hand if this is
a true Spin and we turn the apparatus
over if initially the apparatus told us
that the spin was plus one after we've
turned it over and do the experiment
again it will register minus one so it
seems to indicate that there is a sense
of
directionality and of
course uh yeah the same thing is true no
matter what direction we hold the
apparatus in if we hold the apparatus in
the horizontal
Direction and come along and detect a
spin that we know nothing about we have
not yet made a measurement on it maybe
somebody else has made a measurement on
it maybe some agent unavailable to us
who uh some secret uh uh secret person
has done something to that spin but we
don't care we don't know about it we
come in with our detector and we make a
measurement what will we measure again
we will measure plus one or minus
one and if we're beginning to think of
this thing as having a sense of
direction to it we might say that what
we're measuring now is this x component
of the spin whereas previously we were
measuring the Z component of the spin
let's give them names this Sigma Z which
is the component of the spin along the
vertical axis at the moment yet I'm not
asking you to think that these notion of
component is the same as the notion of
component in classical physics it's just
a name for the moment and sigma Z
whenever it's measured is plus or minus
one the same thing happens when we turn
the apparatus on its side and we measure
the same same procedure we measure
something that we can now call Sigma X
and sigma X is always plus or minus one
and the same thing if we turn the
apparatus around so that it's facing
frontward in fact no matter what
direction we Orient the apparatus it
always gives us plus or minus
one this would be a little bit strange
more than a little bit strange if this
object really were a classical Vector a
little Vector perhaps a vector of unit
length if it were a vector of unit
length and this detector were really
measuring the component of spin along
its own axis there is no way that it
would just give plus or minus
one right components of vectors even if
the vector is required to have exactly
unit length here's a vector with exactly
unit length a uh a pointer a three
Vector of exactly unit length if we turn
it and do other things with it the X
component or the Z component can be any
number between minus1 and one so this is
a funny Vector if it's a vector ctor at
all but still it does seem to have a
sense of
orientation the results of experiments
do seem to change when you rotate
detectors in particular If You
Begin by orienting the Spin along the
z-axis in the up Direction let's call
this up that means Sigma Z is equal to+
one and then rotate the
apparatus detect it again you won't
necess necessarily get + one in fact you
may get plus one or you may get minus
one with equal
probability you could do the experiment
over and over and over
again half the times you would get Sigma
x = +1 half the times you would get
Sigma xal minus1 even though you knew
Sigma Z was exactly + one in each case
so
um something's funny but what is true is
that the average value of Sigma X will
be one sorry will be zero if the initial
starting point was a spin that was up
along the
z-axis same for the y axis if the
initial value of the spin was prepared
to be up along the z-axis and you rotate
the apparatus into the Y
orientation again you'll have equal
probability and so the average value of
Sigma y y will be zero you can even go
beyond that you can say let's start with
the apparatus not vertical but let's
start with the appar the apparatus along
the X
Direction use it to prepare the spin so
that it's known to be pointing
horizontal along the X Direction in
other words Sigma X is equal to + one
and then do a y or Z
experiment always we will get random but
equal probabilities for up and down
or or plus or minus
one you go a little bit
further now of course I am quoting what
would be the results of experiments on
spins I've never done such an experiment
I don't think I
could uh but I have no doubt that if I
had the skill to do it this is what
would
happen What suppose we start out and we
have not prepared
spit it all doesn't matter okay go ahead
so it could be up or down or X or z y we
don't know we don't know what it's we
don't know what it is and we set it up
so that the uh apparatus is on inside
all the x- axis
okay um and we do lots of measurements
we going to what's what's well we first
do one measurement before we do anything
El yeah let me come back for a second
let me let me come back a second
you're right we want to do a lot of
experiments and a lot of measurements in
quantum mechanics there are two distinct
ways we could do lots of experiments it
really doesn't matter which which we do
we could imagine having a large number
of identical spins prepared the
beginning however they were
prepared and we can do experiments on a
large number of them or we can do
repeated experiments on the same
spin to a large extent it doesn't matter
which we're talking about and I'll tell
you when it matters but at the moment
all we're talking about is one
spin you said start the apparatus
horizontal stick the spin into it and
detect what you get what you get will
either be plus one or minus one
okay you could then take the spin out of
there give it to your friend who uh does
some magic with spins you don't know
what it is you you don't know what the
hell he does with it he flips it around
juggles it puts it in his pocket takes
it out and gives it back to you and
tells you to do it again again you'll
get plus one or minus one it may be that
he did nothing in which case the second
time you'll get the same answer you got
the first
time or it may have been that he turned
it over in which case you'll get the
opposite answer but whatever you get it
will be plus one or minus
one okay then if you do a repeated
experiment knowing that nothing else was
done to the spin in between you'll get
the same answer if you do the same
experiment okay that's
uh good okay so let's be a little more
General let's suppose that we Orient the
axis of the detector in any direction so
let's make a notation for a direction a
unit 3 Vector a unit 3
Vector unit vectors in three-dimensional
space are always indicated by putting a
little hat on top of the
symbol so this is a unit Vector along a
particular axis we start with our
detector along the axis
m not horizontal not vertical not in or
out but just a caddy cornered in
some some complicated way there m
there's M
and uh we start with the spin let's
start with with a spin previously having
been oriented or prepared along a
different axis the N
axis how do we do that well I should
have gone I should have gone a little
slower we start with the detector along
the N axis do an experiment and discover
that along the N axis the spin comes up+
one then we rotate the apparatus into
the M
Direction and we do another experiment
on the same spin it will either come up
plus one or minus one along the ma AIS
never in
between but the average value of the
spin along the ma axis here will not be
one one it will not be minus one what
will it be it will be the cosine of the
angle between M and N other words the
component of M along n how do we write
that let's write that let's write a
formula for
that the symbol for averages in quantum
mechanics are a pair of angular brackets
like this this one is called a bra this
one is called a cat and the whole thing
makes a bra k
which is British for
bracket okay the average value of Sigma
M knowing that it was originally
oriented along the N
Direction and measured along the M
direction is the cosine of the angle
between n and M which can also be
written as
n.m the ordinary dotproduct of the
vectors or just the component of n along
M the spin was oriented in the N
Direction You measured it along the M
Direction and the answer is plus or
minus one but on the
average it's what a classical physicist
might have
expected if he measured the component of
a spin which is oriented in One
Direction along some other direction
this is exactly the component of M along
n all right
so uh if you do the experiment many many
times and collect
averages it seems in fact that the
average quantities do behave like
vectors or like three vectors but the
individual experiments are very
resistant to giving any answer other
than plus or minus
one okay so this
now doesn't know how the apparatus
doesn't know how to give any answer
other than plus or minus one doesn't
know how to well doesn't know how to
give any uh you might try to build
another apparatus that does better but
it won't do
better make sure I understand the setup
here you the setup is that you prepare
the um the spin along the N
axis and then you measure it along the
ma axis right and you get a random
answer but random bias
biased in such a way that uh that the
average is n.m that for example would
mean that if n and M were the same
direction that you didn't rotate it at
all what is n.m in that
case one right and that would just be an
indication that you got the same answer
if n was up and you did the experiment
You' get it up and up and up over and
over and over again
okay um wouldn't it be
I want to be very rigorous here wouldn't
it be more accurate to say the expected
value would be n times n rather the
average no no my friend Murray Gilman
loves to say the expected value it is
not the expected
value if I gave you a probability
distribution which look like
this what would be the expected value
that you would have
the expect the least expected value
would be the one right in the middle but
the average value would be the one right
in the
middle okay expected Val expected values
and average values are very different in
general and this is the average value
the average if you average the quantity
that you get in the standard sense of
averaging standard average
it's also called the expectation value
but again that's a misnomer it's not the
it's not the value that you expect
necessarily just want to make sure thing
about this right the spin the only thing
we know about the spin is that when we
measure we get plus one or minus one
that's all really that's all that's well
that's all we know until we start doing
a lot of exper about the Z component of
this and that that all has to do with
results from the apparatus that's right
has nothing to do with the thing I mean
well at least
opor well there are different
experiments that you can do on the
spin the results of those
experiments can be used or the
particular experiment you you you do can
be used to label what it is that you
measured I guess what I guess the point
I'm trying to make is at one point you
were drawing a spin as having an arrow
either up or down and that seem to me of
prejudice it's it's either plus one or
minus one whatever that means we don't
know there's no geometric meaning to it
yeah that's right there's no geometric
meaning to it obviously to begin with
but we did discover that by turning the
this thing over we always get the
opposite sign well that's starting to
tell us there's some difference between
the apparatus up and the apparatus down
it's not not like a thermometer
measuring temperature some notion there
that it's different to uh to be up and
down and then if we turn it on a side we
find out that in some sense it really
does behave on the average like a
vector on the
average
okay but it is what it is but but that
Vector changes depend on how it's been
prepared in other words when you prepare
it you may have an something with an X
component if you've got the apparat one
way but if you have if you prepare it
with the apparat another way
it may have a z component is that
correct yeah
okay yeah but it is what it is and I've
told you the facts the facts are if you
first prepare by putting your apparatus
along One Direction and then measure
with your apparatus along the other
direction the average value of the
result will be
n.m but every single event will be a
plus one or a minus one Nothing Left to
Say say It Anyway slightly different is
that if it's if n and M are along the
same direction or opposite direction
then it isn't just an average it repeats
itself yeah whereas if it's any of the
others it's an average yeah right it's
still an
average
right but if a number or a result can
only be plus or minus one and the
average is plus one it means every event
was plus
one right
okay let's talk about logic a little
bit our problem with quantum mechanics
is that logic the logic of the of
quantum systems is
different than the logic of classical
systems but our brains are classical
systems and incapable of thinking in
Quantum logic nevertheless we can get a
glimmering of what quantum logic is like
by thinking about these
experiments
um we could either talk about the
calculus of
propositions or the nature of the states
of a system the space of states of a
system let's start with the space of
states of a system the space of states
of a system and think classically for a
moment they're a set and they're a set
of possible States here they are
heads
Tails 6 5 4 3 2 1 for the
D particle on a line would have an
infinite number of possible States but
the states form a set of some
type a proposition about the states of
the system is basically a subset it's
the subset of states for which the
proposition is true okay so uh for the
D my proposition is the die shows an
even
face that's a proposition and it's true
for half the states of the die and so it
corresponds to a subset 2 four and six
right there's the contradictory
statement the not statement not the die
shows an even face which obviously
equivalent to the statement the D shows
an odd
face and so
In classical
Logic the not of a statement the not
means the contradiction of the statement
if this is the statement meaning to say
it's true for all the subset of states
in here the not statement is the
statement uh is the complement or the
collection of things which are
not in
there okay let's uh let's go to our spin
proposition the spin is up along the
z-axis what's the knot of that the knot
of that is if we measure the spin along
the z-axis we get something else other
than one the only other possibility is
minus one so spin equal minus one along
the z-axis is the not
statement of the spin is up along the
z-axis so logic uh logic makes some
sense but we begin to find very peculiar
differences when we start talking about
the operations of
combining propositions through the use
of and and
or and and or are different in quantum
mechanics than they are in classical
mechanics I want to I want to lay that
out it's so interesting and so rarely
explained that uh that I I sort of like
to uh to explain it
yeah not there and if I this correctly
in the classical example like the d The
Universal set is finite in terms of the
number of elements in it number of
states in it and the then you jump to
the cons example and it seems like that
would be infinite because all the
possible times does that make a
difference all the possible what all the
possible experiments that you could do
is not limited yeah okay you're getting
at something important which we're going
to get to um it's clear that in some
sense the number of states of this spin
is finite it's just up or down if we
measure it along the
z-axis on the other hand it also looks
like we can tilt our apparatus in any
direction and prepare the state in any
oriented along any direction so it looks
like there's an infinite ambiguity in
the state of a system this is what this
is the whole point of of trying to
understand the states of systems to
understand the
connection between the continuously
different direction that the electron
could point in and the fact that anytime
we measure it along a given axis it's
only up or down but we'll come to it
it's a good question but we'll come to
it okay let's
uh let's talk about the prop calculus of
propositions if I give you two
propositions A and B I can form two
combinations of them a or B and A and B
let's just see see what that means in
terms of uh
sets if we have two propositions this
one is a this one is
B then a and b means the set of states
which belong both to a and to B right so
it's the intersection of the set a and
the set B called logically the
intersection or set theoretically the
intersection
is basically the end
operation this point is in a and it's in
B okay that's
straightforward the and any given any
two
propositions you can always
form the uh oh and or another way to say
it the right way to say it is this is
the set of points in here for which the
proposition A and B is true true A and B
is true in here and it is true nowhere
else okay what
about what about these two subsets A and
B A and B is still a
proposition but it's always false there
is no uh there is no state for which A
and B is true
all right so there are A's and B's that
you can put together I mean um my friend
Sanjay over here is uh uh weighs 600 lb
and uh my friend uh that's not a good
one there are combinations for which A
and B is always false
obviously right in particular if you
take a and not a it's always
false all right but still the definition
of A and B is the intersection and it's
true for all the states in the
intersection or is a little more
complicated or at least there are two
versions of or there is the exclusive or
and the inclusive or in the English
language we usually when we use the word
or we usually mean the exclusive or when
we say that
uh
um I am Jewish and I am Catholic or I'm
Catholic I ordinarily mean that I can't
be both right that I can't be both and
so the usual or is the exclusive or the
one you normally think about but in
Logic the term or is the inclusive or it
means
a it's true if a is true it's true if B
is true and it's true if both of them
are true it's the inclusive
or uh so I can correctly
say um I am a physicist and I am a
father that's true but I can also say I
am a physicist or I am a father and it
is also true why because both of them
are true so that's the inclusive or
inclusive or corresponds to the union of
two sets if I have a and I have B then
the inclusive or is everything in both
sets or either
set okay anything not in both sets
anything in either set or in both
sets the exclusive or would correspond
to things in one set but not the other
set the exclusive of or
includes uh we will always when whenever
I speak of the of or I always mean the
inclusive
or okay so that's and an or
what else can you say about them not
very
much yeah we're going to we're going to
now use that concept to try to formulate
a set of and and or statements about the
spin and then ask how would you verify
them how would you verify them how would
you verify them and does it mean
anything to verify
them okay so let's take the two
propositions A and B to
be Sigma
Z is equal to +
one +
one and sigma X this is a and this is B
Sigma X is equal to + one they're both
propositions we would know how to check
either one of them if we wanted to check
Sigma a we so the first a we would turn
our apparatus vertically upward and
measure the spin and we would check it
and see true or false if we wanted to
find out if B was true or false we would
turn the apparatus on its side right in
classical
logic if there are two propositions you
can form the combination A or B let's
start with A or B so we'll take a or
b and let's think about checking its
truth value is it true or is it not all
right so I we'll we'll design an
experiment to try to oh oh and let's uh
go back a step let's imagine the hidden
ghost in the works has uh previously
unknown to us unknown to us has
originally oriented the spin upward
along the z-axis it's he knows we don't
as far as we know we know nothing but uh
the ghost in the works has oriented the
spin vertically upward just and it
doesn't this doesn't matter but we could
start that way so the spin is upward and
let's check whether a or b is true how
do we begin let's begin by measuring the
spin along the z-axis we put our
detector or our apparatus in the
vertical
Direction and we measure what do we
get we get plus one we get plus one
because the ghost in the works has uh
has made it up one to begin with we
don't have to go any further A or B is
true A or B includes the possibility
that both A and B are true but all it
requires to be true is that one of them
is true and we've just discover that a
is true so A or B is definitely
true but now let's do the experiment in
another way in in a in in an order which
would not matter if we were doing
classical physics and the reason it
doesn't matter when we do classical
physics
is when we do an experiment it has no
necessary effect on the outcome of a
later experiment if the experiment is
gentle enough so let's do the experiment
in the opposite
order instead of first finding out
whether a is true let's first ask if B
is true and then we'll come back and ask
if a is true all right secretly the spin
is pointing up in the Z Direction so the
ghost knows that but we don't and so we
come along knowing nothing about the
spin and say why should I measure why
should I measure a first let's first
measure B let's first measure the X
component of the spin and what do we
get we get either plus one or minus one
we get plus one or minus one with a 50%
probability so there's a 50% probability
that b is + one but if B is not Plus +
one it doesn't mean that a plus b a A or
B is wrong we still have the chance that
when we measure a it'll be+
one okay but the problem is that in
measuring B the first time
around we Orient we prepare b along the
x-axis whatever we get whether it's this
way or this
way we have prepared that spin along the
x-axis what will the next experiment
give when we measure it along the
z-axis 50% probability of being up and
50% probability of
down that means we have a 25%
probability of
finding both that Sigma X was equal to
minus1 and sigma Z is equal to
minus1 we have a 50% probability in the
first
experiment that Sigma X was not equal to
1 and then in the next experiment we
have another 50% probability on top of
that that Sigma Z was not equal to one
so we have a net probability of one
quarter that both A and B were
false when we did the experiment in one
order when we do the experiment in the
other order it is certain that A or B is
right why because a is right
so what is true in classical physics
that the idea of a or b is symmetrical
between A and B the idea of the or
statement A or B if a or b is true then
b or a is true and we find that in
quantum
mechanics the concept of A or B at
best can only be defined in a way that
depends on the order in which you
determine A or
B Ian I say that the two propositions
are incompletely specified in the
quantum mechanical case because you have
to give the order right a it isn't like
the particle has a certain xpin
independent of how you handle it right
would you say that's right yeah I
would but
um I would also say that any attempt
to think of a logic of experiments will
be different than um quantum mechanics
thearchy between A and B why the what
hierarchy what hierarchy in other words
A and B if you measure a then you
certain of B if you measure B then you
aren't certain of a but you're certain
no no no no no let's go back I said the
ghost in the Woodwork has made the spin
to be pointing up along the
z-axis that's a we don't know that but
it's true
Okay then if we measure Sigma Z first
under those circumstances we will surely
find that A or B is
true but if we measure under under the
same
circumstances the same degree of lack or
or presence of knowledge we measure B
first we find out that there's a 25%
chance that A or B this this composite
statement here is false so a question
the the operation A or B the result is
now going to be a probability it's going
to be 25 instead of Z or well not only
that but you have to specify which order
you determine A and B right so that's in
itself an element of something new that
the or statement does not unify two
statements into a symmetrical uh in a
symmetrical
way
question
um I'm confused when we uh the the thing
has been prepared so that it's up we
don't know it's been prepared y we then
you know that doesn't that didn't matter
just to simplify the story I said that
it wouldn't have mattered but we we then
do the experiment we do B test by
turning machine the apparatus on its
side and I thought what you had said is
if we now do this multiple times we'll
get an average yeah but we're not doing
it we're trying to find out but but
you're saying we're going to prepare you
what you're saying is when we do that
first measurement on its side we're
preparing the the spin again and that
would say then then from then on we
should always get plus one if if we
compare plus one for Sigma X but then if
we do Sigma Z we'll get a random
answer measuring oneand we're going to
get we're going to get a we're going to
get a random answer for the first
measurement of Sig
X about
I can't I can't stop the class to uh
okay question if we have a measurement
device to measure two different uh
particles and uh why have you gotten why
have you jumped the two particles okay
uh I was just wondering the act of
measurement does it in inductively
spread
backwards what
okay that was all
review all right the next thing which I
was going to review but I'm not going to
because it took too
long there Vector
spaces I'll just remind you real quickly
Vector spaces are sets of elements you
can add elements this is not something
you would
do with
sets you can add two sets of course to
make a bigger set but uh there's no
natural single element which is the sum
of two
elements uh so the elements of set
theory namely the basic individual
objects are not things that you can add
and make new
elements um the space of states of a
Quantum system is a linear Vector space
and that means given any two states you
can add them in some sense and make make
another state and that's what we're
going to
explore uh this logic this peculiar
logic and this peculiar Distortion of
logic turns out to be the logic of
vector spaces it's a logic which is
embedded in the structure of vector
spaces in a very neat and uh tidy way
and that's why ultimately why Vector
spaces are
important okay so let's just remember
vectors are things that you can add
if there are two vectors A and B you can
add them you can multiply them by
complex
numbers every Vector has a dual Vector
which is kind of its complex
conjugate if we call these objects K
vectors because they are the second half
of a
braet
then the K the bra vectors which are in
onetoone correspondence which are
uh for every K Vector there is a bra
Vector but it's uh its status is that of
a complex conjugate so there's two dual
Vector
spaces and you can take inner products
of vectors a bra Vector with a K Vector
okay so the bra vector and the K Vector
can be combined together it gives a
complex number the inner product is a
complex
number and it's satisfies that it is
equal to the complex
conjugate complex conjugate
of the opposite
order so when you take a complex Vector
in a complex Vector space and you take
the inner product if you interchange the
two vectors then that's equivalent to
complex conjugation that's pretty much
what you need to
know that allows you to Define how
giving given the idea of a in a product
that allows you to define the notion of
the length of a
vector we usually don't think about the
length of the vector we usually think
about the square of the length of the
vector and the square of the length of a
vector let's say the vector is a is the
inner product with its own conjugate or
with its own
duel usually we say it's the inner
product with itself but that's a sort of
slight abusive terminology and this is
always real the reason it's always real
is because if we interchange a and a we
just get back to the same thing but this
tells us that the inner product of a
Anda is its own complex conjugate being
its own complex conjugate it's
real it's also positive that's easy to
prove and it can be thought of as the
square of the length of a
vector it's analogous to closely
analogous to the dotproduct
of a three Vector with
itself if a and b were three vectors
then we wouldn't distinguish the bra and
the and the K but we would write that a
do B is the dot product between two
vectors analogous to this and we would
also write that a.
a was the square of the length of
a okay so the inner product of a vector
with itself can be thought of as a
square of the length of the
vector and finally there is the notion
of
orthogonality two vectors are orthogonal
when their inner product is
zero
orthogonal same definition as for DOT
product when the dot product between two
vectors is zero those vectors are
orthogonal
those are the definitions that we need
for a vector
space the other definition is the
definition of the dimensionality of the
vector space how many dimensions does a
vector space have and the way to decide
that is by asking what's the maximum
number of orthogonal vectors that you
can find in the vector space for
ordinary vectors let's say in two three
four dimensions this is obvious in two
Dimensions I can pick a vector just pick
any Vector make it a unit Vector just by
shrinking its length until it's of unit
length and then I look around and I see
if I can find another orthogonal Vector
to it yeah in fact I can find two one
point's this way and one point's that
way but that's not that's not an
important distinction we find one other
direction or one other Vector apart from
uh apart from a numerical multiple apart
from a numerical multiple there is one
other Vector which is orthogonal to it
and so there are two
mutually the maximum number of mutually
orthogonal vectors that you can find is
two if you go to three directions you
can find a third one but no more try to
find a fourth one and you run out of
directions so three-dimensional space
has three mutually orthogonal vectors
four-dimensional space has four and so
forth and the same thing is true of
complex Vector
spaces we Des described a version of
complex Vector spaces which were just
column
vectors alpha 1 Alpha 2 Alpha 3 dot dot
dot and their du which were row
vectors which were made up out of the
complex conjugate
variables and so once we have a vector
we can start looking for orthogonal
vectors to it vectors which are
perpendicular in this sense
find another one then look for a third
one look for a fourth
one however many you find you'll
eventually run out of directions that's
the dimensionality of the space for the
special case in which there are only two
entries
here it's a two-dimensional Vector space
you can only find two mutually
orthogonal
vectors you can find many pairs of
mutually orthogonal vectors and just in
a real space there's these there's these
there's these Point them in any
direction but once you find two of them
there won't be another
one okay so we have the idea of mutually
orthogonal
vectors and now we have to State what is
the connection between a vector space
and the space of possible states of a
Quantum
system the quantum system that we're
going to deal with is still this very
primitive and simple single spin until
we get the handle on that we won't want
to move to more complicated
things is there any restriction
that the orthogonal vectors have to be
perpendicular to each other that's what
orthogonal means well suppose you have a
a cube and then you sort of tilt it like
a parallelogram it's still
three-dimensional but the coordinate
systems are not perpendicular one of
them is not perpendicular and orthogonal
are synonymous terms
perpendicular and orthogonal both mean
right
angle you're confused by something and I
don't know what it
is
H yeah yeah I know you
are
but perpendicular orthogonal right
angles they mean all the same things I
think you think of linearly independ
being but if you have a set of larpent
vectors you can extract anal out of them
this is true he's not he's not
confused this is
right linearly independent is different
than orthogonal orthogonal is linearly
independent but linearly independent is
less strong than
orthogonal these two vectors like that
they're linearly independent but they're
not orthogonal those are
orthogonal okay okay let's we'll come
back all right the states of a Quantum
system this is a
postulate form a vector space form a
complex Vector space in fact the space
of the simple system we've been
discussing form a two-dimensional Vector
space let's write down some vectors we
know some states we know for example
that there is a state that can be
prepared in which the spin is pointing
upward along the
z-axis we characterize the state by the
experiment that we did to get it in that
state that
experiment had the apparatus vertically
upward and it created a state of the
system which either could have been down
or up but let's say it's
up we can label that state in a number
of ways we can call it up we can call it
down we can call it plus we can call it
well up and down are the same as plus
and minus we could draw them with little
arrows up and down what other ways could
we ah we could write it as Sigma Z = +
one and sigma zal minus1 they all mean
the same thing up
down plus minus Sigma Z + one Sigma Z
Min - one all the same thing all right
so there are two states that we know
about that we can
access by putting the uh or we can
prepare by turning our apparatus upward
along the z-axis let's give them names
these states are vectors in a vector
space according to
hypothesis and they can be called let's
say up and
down if it is true that the vector space
is as simple as just a the
two-dimensional Vector space then that
means that any Vector in that space can
be written as some linear combination of
up and
down in other words every Vector in a
two-dimensional space can be written in
terms of two basis vectors up and
down so that's enough to write any state
whatever up
down all right what about though the
state which is made by tilting our
apparatus along the
x-axis we get something different it's
not the same thing it's not up because
up means up along the
z-axis it's not down because down means
down along the z- axis and we know
they're different because we know the
results of experiments on these two
different kinds of states will in
general be
different
so we can call those States
I tend to call them left and right
there's up and down there's right and
left those are two other states we could
draw them this way if we
liked they also correspond to Sigma x =
1 and sigma X =
minus1 and we could label them if we
liked let's label them right and
left finally we know that if if we were
to turn our apparatus so that the uh the
apparatus was pointing along the Y
AIS we could access two more we could
access two more States I think we call
those in and out into the Blackboard and
out of the Blackboard and so there's in
and
out into the Blackboard now of the
Blackboard and they correspond to Sigma
yal plus or minus one
we could label them
in and
out all of the logic that I've described
to you in all of the experimental
results as we will see we will not see
it immediately it took some time to
understand all of this it is all
summarized by a few statements but the
first of which is that the space of all
states of that simple system is
two-dimensional has only two independent
states which
means that these other things can be
written in terms of up and
down Okay so let's uh let's go to
General linear combinations of up and
down and ask what they mean let's take a
vector I guess we can call it a a which
is of the form a coefficient a complex
coefficient alha Al
1 time up plus another complex con
another I suppose we should call this
Alpha up Alpha up Alpha down times down
the alphas are complex
numbers in complex Vector spaces you
multiply they could be real numbers but
in general they will be complex
numbers let us suppose we knew what that
meant what kind of state was where it
came from it's some new Beast it's not
up it's not down some was in
[Music]
between next postulate the next
postulate is that if we were to measure
up and down if we if somebody prepared
us an electron or a spin in this state
and we measured up and down we would
find probabilities for up and down and
those probabilities would be probability
for up
is the square of the
magnitude of this
coefficient and probability for
down is equal to Alpha star down Alpha
down in other words it's basically the
square of the coefficient or the square
of the
component of a in the directions up and
down these Alphas they're essentially
the components of a general Vector along
the two axes up and
down there's something that I failed to
tell you it's also a postulate there are
many many postulates but you'll see they
fit together in a neat package there are
probably fewer par postulates than I'm
uh than I'm
saying uh I'll bet we could reduce it
down to four postulates four axioms but
uh rather than trying to aati it we'll
just uh
uh uh do it a little more
informally what's the relation between
up and
down are they the negative of each
other no they're orthogonal now that's
postulate the basic postulate is when
things are measurably different when two
states are such that you can cleanly
tell the difference between them by an
experiment they are
orthogonal orthogonality literally means
they
are sufficiently different that you can
with a single experiment tell the or
maybe a few experiments tell the
difference between them
uniquely I'll tell you what it
corresponds to in terms of
sets you might say that two sets are
orthogonal if they don't share any
element elements this is not a standard
terminology but you might say it anyway
they're orthogonals that don't share any
elements that means that distinctly
different there's no chance that an
experiment will confuse the two of them
experiment will a nice experiment to
distinguish them will not lead to any
ambiguity the same is true of up and
down up is distinctly different than
down if you measure up you'll measure up
again and again and again and the
version of that in quantum mechanics
uh or the implication of that in Quantum
Mechanics for the vectors is that things
that correspond to physically
unambiguous different situations are
orthogonal to each other so up and down
are orthogonal to each
other what if we have a combination of
up and down with some
coefficients then there's a probability
to be up and a probability to be down
and the probabilities are given by Alpha
star
Alpha up and Alpha star Alpha
down again that's a postulate but we'll
see in a moment what that corresponds
to
well what's the relation between the
probability for up and the probability
for down the answer is that if we add
them we get
one and therefore Alpha star Alpha plus
beta star beta is equal to
1 any reasonable able state of the
system which has total probability one
for all the different things that can
happen should satisfy that the sum of
the probabilities of the distinct
probabilities should add up to one and
so that says that Alpha star
Alpha plus beta not beta Alpha up up
plus Alpha Down star Alpha down did I
use beta before no okay should equal one
but that's
equivalent to the statement that the
inner product of a with
itself is equal to
one when we think
about prove
this prove that Alpha star Alpha summed
over up and down down is equal to the
inner product of a with itself it does
follow from the
postulates it does follow from the
postulates and the assumption that U and
D are perpendicular unit
vectors U and D are perpendicular unit
vectors make that assumption they're
orthogonal to each other they're unit
vectors if they're not unit vectors you
can change them until they are unit
vectors and then you can prove that the
inner product of a vector with itself
self is just the sums of the squares or
the conjugates times
itself okay so that's that's a little
thing to prove but what does that say
that says that a physical state
corresponds to a vector in the vector
space of unit length a unit
Vector the unit standing for the fact
that the total probability is one all
right so
States not only equal vectors in a
vector space but they unit
vectors the other term for unit vectors
is normalized
vectors
normalized
vectors normalized is another word for
unit so all physical States all states
of what you can do to that electron spin
or to anything else
correspond to unit
vectors and given any such unit
Vector the probabilities associated with
it are alpha star Alpha up and Alpha
star Alpha down right so that uh that is
a bit of
information but wait a minute what
happened to these other vectors right
and
left what happened to right and
left right and left seem like different
states but according to the
postulate right and left must be linear
combinations of up and down that's not
too
surprising because if you prepare right
or left and then measure up or down you
get plus one or minus one that's all
there is plus one or minus one
so it's not too surprising that whatever
right or left is it's somehow a
combination of up and
down and that
statement is
buried in the properties of
vectors so let's look at the state left
no let's look at the state right what do
we know about it well we know that it
must be a
combination Alpha up up up plus Alpha
down down we can also write that in the
form of a column Vector Alpha up and
Alpha
down number one number two supposing an
electron is created pointing along the
right
direction the x- axis what are the
probabilities for it to be up and down
remember half half that means that Alpha
up star Alpha up must equal a half and
Alpha star down Alpha
down must equal a
half okay let's make a guess let's make
a guess the simplest guess would be to
put 1/ < TK of two and 1 over square of
two
here Alpha up is 1/ > two if Alpha is
1un of two what's Alpha star
Alpha 12 okay this one's also 1/2 now we
could put other we could put some we
could put some other things what
ambiguity is there we could put a minus
sign
here or we could put a complex
coefficient in front of here without
changing the magnitude of it we'll come
back to that we'll come back to what
that
means we'll come back to what that
ambiguity
means but let's take this as a working
hypothesis for what the state right is
that leaves us with the state
left what do we know about left well
right and left are physically
distinguishable by a single
experiment you can Orient your apparatus
along the X Direction measure Sigma X
and determine unambiguously whether it
corresponds to right or
left what does that mean about the
vectors right and left it means they're
orthogonal orthogonal and physically
measurably distinct are the same things
so that tells us that left right should
be equal to zero incidentally we have
assumed that up down is equal to
zero up down or
Al by symmetry basically there's nothing
different about the x-axis than the
z-axis so if the two vectors up and down
are orthogonal it stands the reason that
the two vectors left and right must be
orthogonal here's right is there a
vector that's orthogonal to it yeah
there there is a vector which is
orthogonal to it what is
it 1/ > two up minus 1 /k of two down
down now it's ambiguous whether you put
the minus sign here or here either way
will work and we'll find out that
there's no physical difference between
those two
possibilities we'll find out later that
there's no physics in the overall sign
of uh of a
vector so here's one which is orthogonal
how do we check that this is orthogonal
to that well let's let's write the the
row let's write the here's the column
Vector describing
right let's write down the row Vector no
that's not the column Vector here's the
column Vector the column Vector
describing right is 1 overun of two 1
over < TK of
two that's these two what is the row
Vector describing left if we want to
take the inner product we want to
combine the row Vector with the column
Vector so the row Vector describing this
guy over here is 1/ < TK two minus 1
over < TK
two and to take the inner product
between them you take the product of the
first coefficient times the first
coefficient plus the product of the
second one times the second one standard
rule for taking the inner product
between a column vector and a row Vector
you match the first component with the
first component multiply them second
component with the second component
multiply them and go right down through
the uh through all the components and
add them
up okay so what's the
answer2 sorry 1 of2 * 1 > two that's a
half minus 1 of2 * 1 of2 this inner
product is zero so we found a second
Vector which corresponds to right and
left a candidate if you like for right
and
left and what's more you'll notice that
this Vector also has the property that
there's that the probability for it to
be up and down is equal to a half for
each
one why because the square of this is
1/2 and the square of the magnitude of
this one is 1/2 so we have a nice
symmetrical relationship between left
right and up and
down incidentally it's kind of
interesting supposing um where's my
Eraser your
yeah it's kind of interesting I've
written right and left in terms of up
and down I could of course write up and
down in terms of right and left let's
see what we get if we add these two
equations the Downs will cancel and
we'll just get up we'll get two over
we'll get square of 2 that's 2 over the
< TK of 2 *
up equals right plus left
and then divide by < TK of
two and we'll find that
down is equal to right minus left over <
TK of two so you see there's a complete
reciprocal relationship between them um
if
we began our
experiments with our apparatus along the
X direction we might have
started we might have started with left
and right and come to the conclusion
that up and down are combinations of
left and
right okay that leaves in and out what
about in and-
out is there a third pair of vectors in
and out which stand in the same
relationship to right and left and to
left to right and left and to up and
down as they stand to each other is
there a third combination which has uh
which is
symmetrically defined all right let's
let's put it up
here we have up and
down and they're orthogonal to each
other we have right and left right which
is equal to 1/ < TK two we can write it
as up plus
down and
left same thing 1/ > two time up minus
down we also have right left equal to
zero moreover we have something that I'm
not going to write but I'll say it
anyway if you start and right and you
say what's the probability for up and
down it's 1/2 if you start with left
then ask what's the probability for up
and down it's 1/2 what happens if you
start with up and down what's the
probability for right and
left well it's also one half we know
that's one half from the physics of the
situation but it's also true that when I
rewrite up and down in terms of right
and left the coefficients are also 1/ <
TK of two so they're nice and
symmetrically related to each other all
right so that leaves us with the last
possibility or the last perpendicular
Direction in
out okay so let's try to guess it's
going to have an up and it's going to
have plus a
down but there's going to be some
coefficients here we don't know what
those coefficients are
yet what do we know about the
coefficients they're complex in general
in general they're
complex mod squ has to be one the square
has to the the magnitude of this square
has to be
1/2 we also know that the coefficients
here have to be such that in and out are
perpendicular to each
other and we also should
find that if we rewrite in and
out in terms of left and right he the
coefficients should also have modulus 1
12 just by
symmetry turns out that's enough to
determine them completely I'm not going
to prove it that's a homework assignment
it's a nice homework assignment let's
see what the requirements are the
requirements are that in out equals
zero that both in or out when written in
terms of up or
down should have
coefficients whose magnitude is a
half squared magnitude is a half and
also when written in terms of left and
right the same corresponding
coefficients here should have magnitude
plus or minus a
half that is enough to determine the
coefficients in terms in terms of up and
down with a small ambiguity which is not
interesting I'll tell you later what
that ambiguity is has no physics in
it first of all is the overall sign of
the vectors that has no physics in it as
we'll see we'll find out all right what
is the solution the solution is one here
and I
here with a square root of two we have
to put a one over Square < TK of Two and
a one over squ Ro of
two and out is the same
thing minus I over <
tk2
down let's write it in terms of column
and row vectors should that be an i over
two on the on the end Vector let one
well have I I
there is that what you're
asking I actually had it right it was 1
time I
good all
right we can write these in terms of
column vectors let's write the various
column vectors
up what would you write for
up well we could write one
zero up is just up with no with no down
component
down is just 01
a one in the down place and a zero in
the up place what
about
right that's equal to 1 / < TK 2 1/ < TK
left that's equal
[Music]
to 1 /un 2 - 1/ <
tk2 and now let's
put
in N is 1 over < TK
two I over < TK
2 and WR uh sorry out is equal to I uh 1
over < TK of
two minus I over <
tk2 first
question is this orthogonal to
this how do we
check we take this times the complex
conjugate of this plus this times the
complex conjugate of this that's the
rule for calculating inner products we
could construct the row vectors we don't
need to oh let's let's let's let's no we
don't need to remember that the row
vectors have complex conjugate
entries all right but it's easy enough
to do just the inner product the inner
product is the sum of the products of
the
entries times that complex
conjugate all right so one of these has
to be complex conjugated what's the
product of this with its complex
conjugate one2 time one it's just
1/2 so this one times this one gives you
a
1/2 and how about this times the complex
conjugate of
this minus 12us
12- I over 2 what's the complex
conjugate of
I2 minus I two so we have to multiply
minus I overk of2 * another minus I
overun two which gives us minus a
half I * I is minus one so that gives us
minus a half and if we add them up we
get zero so yes these two are orthogonal
to each
other the magnitude of the coefficients
here the square of the magnitude of the
coefficients are each equal to a half
which proves that if you're in the
instate or the outstate the probability
of being up or down
is2 how about the probability of being
left or right how might you figure that
out say it again I I
defin definition of I is that it's the
square root of minus
one so I * I is always minus
one I is not oh sorry this uh this I is
not in
no this okay
I and
out right and left
up can stay the way it is and
down and now go back through that all of
the pages and change it not
important actually we could have changed
it more easily just change this I to
Capital I but uh that would be a bad
that would be bad form bad
form okay is there anything about this
coordinate system that that could imply
a left or right-handed coordinate system
like like a cross yal Z very very good
question the answer is yes but we'll
come to it yes that's a very very good
question
um what is it that's in here that is
telling us that it's a right-handed
coordinate system rather than a
left-handed coordinate system and I
didn't want to go there yet we'll come
to it we'll come to it when we explore
the POI
matrices but uh for the moment we're
just uh we're doing we're sort of
guessing away bumbling through
trying to find vectors which describe uh
the various states of the
system okay this is my proposal if you
like my best guess at the moment for
what the states up down those those are
Bas that's you start with those in terms
of those what right and left are and
what in and out are now what you could
do we saw that you could rewrite up and
down in terms of left and
right I showed you how to do that and
that means you could write I and O in
terms of left and
right you could check what the
coefficients are I hesitate to do it
because I'm sure I'll Bumble
it on the other hand I'm tempted to do
it because I'm sure I'll get it
right I'll take one shot at it shot if
it doesn't work
out okay up is left plus right down is
left minus right with a square root of
two so let's see if we can figure out
what in is first let's just do
in in is 1 over the < TK of two times up
what did I say up
was up I said was left Plus
is left plus
right left plus
right but with a one over square with
another one overun of two so that gives
me a 1
12 that's left over two plus right over
two
that's
scary and then plus
I over < TK of
two times down anybody remember what
down
was left minus right over the square so
that gives me another that would give
me
left
right over another < TK of two minus
left over another < TK of
two all right so the whole thing looks
like second term has
two only
one the second term no go back that one
right there you got half and then
got
yeah and this can just be
12 theun of Two and a sare and that's
gone away right do I have it
right good okay so what do we get we get
a coefficient times left all right so
here we are
I is equal
to 12
minus I 1 - I over 2 is that
right 1 - I over 2 *
left plus I think it's 1 + I / 2 *
right you mean WR o instead of I there
here are we doing I or o I think
doing but I'm not sure doesn't
matter uh I think we were doing this
one up is left plus right and down is
left minus right with the same ey so I
think uh I think that's right okay now
What's the magnitude of the two
coefficients here then times their
complex conjugates let's check that I
don't see any square roots of two in
this thing do you see any square roots
of two in here you might have expected
some square roots of two
huh nevertheless I maintain that if you
take this times its complex conjugate I
hope to God it's
true I maintain that if you take this
times its complex conjugate you will get
1/2 let's check
it it's 1 - I * 1 +
I over 2 * 2 is
4 1 - I * 1 + I oh praise the Lord is
two is 2 over 4 which is equal to
12 in other words this coefficient here
although it doesn't contain any explicit
square root of two it times its complex
conjugate is equal to 1/ two so the
magnitude of this complex number here is
1 over theun of two it's written in a
form that you don't see any explicit
one/ roots of two but the magnitude of
this is 1 over < TK of two and so is the
magnitude of this the
implication is that if you started in
the state I into the
Blackboard and instead of measuring up
or
down you measured left or right the
probability would be a
half all right so we
found three mutually relate they're not
orthogonal to each other up and down and
not orthogonal to left and right and
they're they're orthogonal to each other
but they're not orthogonal in the
vertical Direction but each
one if expanded in any of the others
would have coefficients whose magnitude
was 1 over theare < TK of two
so they're symmetrically related in that
sense
and what this means in effect is that if
you start with any one of them and
measure the other component if you start
with up or down and measure Sigma X or
Sigma y you'll get probability a
half no matter what you start with any
one of these three combination any one
of these six combinations
and measure a perpendicular combination
you'll always get probability plus or
minus a half now I've put in here some
some uh some postulate about what
probabilities are without telling you
but uh but I think we're coming along
pretty well we have some mathematics
here which is telling us that this that
these um three collections of pairs of
vectors are nicely symmetrically related
to each other
uh
and
that well that's the most important
fact
yes we have
yeah yes
Kevin no no we don't have to
this is orthogonal to this oh oh I'm
sorry three
bases diens that's three bases at angles
with respect to each
other that's a good question the
question is could we find oh excellent
question could we find
another
double let's call it um
big and little no we already used little
L uh fat and skinny
yeah fat and skinny can we find another
pair such that fat is orthogonal to
skinny and the inner product that's what
it come that's what it actually came
down to or that the expansion
coefficients of each one in terms of the
other kind of basis are always equal to
1/ < TK of two or always2 in magnitude
the answer is no there is no
third or no fourth combination that's in
the same relationship now that's that's
not obvious that's not obvious that's
not it is the fact that we live in a
three-dimensional world it's exactly the
fact that we live in a three-dimensional
world right it's exactly the fact it's
the statement that the three dimensions
of space can be
represented in two dimensional uh in two
dimensional Vector space terms all right
let me tell you something else which is
true if I give you a column Vector let's
say a column
Vector alpha 1 Alpha 2 or just the
coefficients of
expansion Alpha up and Alpha down if you
like
the question is how much freedom is
there in the alphas such that it doesn't
change the physical nature of the state
how much Freedom does every combination
of alpha up and Alpha down correspond to
a different state the answer is no first
of all
the total probability has to add up to
one so that's one constraint right there
that Alpha up star Alpha up plus Alpha
Down star Alpha
down is equal to
one there's another fact that we have
not got to yet but we will find that
every physically observable
quantity always associated with a state
always involves an alpha times a complex
conjugate Alpha we will find that we'll
find it it's we won't put it in it will
emerge as one of the consequences of the
postulates but what it says is that if
you
multiply both of the alphas here by the
same phase Factor does everybody know
what a phase factor
is a phase factor is a complex number of
the form e to the I
Theta of unit length doesn't change the
magnitude of either coefficient here
that if we multiply
every entry by the same phase Factor it
doesn't affect anything that means that
if I were to just give you two complex
numbers here there are two redundant
pieces of information that really don't
have anything to do with the physical
character of the state the first is the
overall
magnitude because the overall magnitude
should always be such that the sums of
the squares of these add up to one so
that means it's
one call it a constraint if you like and
a redundancy the redundancy is that if
you multiply both entries by the same
phase Factor here it also doesn't change
the
state so then you could ask how many
independent variables are there which
characterize the state of the system of
this system how many of them are there
well let's
count there are two independent
variables if we don't worry about either
of these constraints here how many
things does it take to characterize two
complex
numbers four four real numbers right but
now one of them doesn't count because we
have to satisfy the constraint that the
total length of this is equal to
one one of them doesn't count but also
another one doesn't count because the
overall phase if we were to multi mply
everything by the same phase Factor here
it also doesn't
count doesn't change the nature of the
state so two of those four
parameters uh are irrelevant to the
physical character of the state how many
is that leave over two two real
numbers how many numbers does it take to
characterize the direction of a unit
Vector two
what are they called longitude and
latitude or something like that just the
direction of a vector can be
characterized by two
angles these
two pairs of numbers are the
same the fact that uh that it takes two
real parameters to
describe a two component Vector like
this is closely related to the fact that
it takes two real angles to describe the
direction
of a three Vector in ordinary
threedimensional
space if we would have added or more
components here it would have been more
complicated so yes there was a deep
connection between the fact very deep
connection between the fact that we only
find three independent uh combinations
like this where are they three
independent combinations and that fat
and skinny never uh uh
we can't find fat and skinny basically
they won't be there not without
increasing the dimensionality of the
vector space that is in fact very deeply
connected to three dimensions of space
yeah uh if space was nine-dimensional or
something like that we would not be able
to represent the directions of a uh
little arrow in it quantum mechanically
by two components
vectors we would need more components
yeah it seems like it seems like just
physically you would take three because
two to specify the direction and then
you got to say whether it's plus one or
minus one right oh no no no the plus one
no no the plus one and minus one are uh
inherit in the the basis right yeah yeah
so so how does this scale up if you had
like three
complex numbers in your vector space I
mean if you wanted to study some higher
dimensional space Oh God we have to
figure it out I don't know how many
question is how many directions how many
parameters are there to um you know it's
more
complicated I that one I'm not going to
try
now right I
did I gotta I gotta tell you I got
really scared when I realized that we
weren't going to get any square roots of
two by doing
this the experiments you described agree
with this math and this math is B on or
correlates with there being three space
it is yes all of what you say is true if
you said there's nine Dimensions would
this this experiment still agree with
there would be a version of it there
would be a version of it it would be
more
complicated and you couldn't describe
the spin of a particle by just a thing
with two components like this it would
take more components what kind of
apparatus would you
spinner
Theory similar things similar
things don't try to look this is enough
for now understanding this um if we went
to four-dimensional space we would need
four component objects but uh that uh
but it grows in yeah three to four would
be yeah you said the states U sort of
correspond to insector what about the
other what about nonunit vectors they
have any interest here at
all
uh well of course if you add two unit
vectors you can get a non-unit vector
you can but then the rule for the states
of a system are divided through divided
through by an overall Factor until it's
normalized they they have the same
significance as probability
distributions which don't sum up to
one you can always go back and say if
somehow somewhere is along the line I
got some answers for probabilities that
added up to something greater than one
well I would just divide through by the
total probability to uh to Define
normalized probability
distributions
so um in intermediate steps of
calculations there might well be the
presence of vectors which are not
normalized but at the end of the day the
states of the system are normalized
vectors
normalized vectors and with no memory of
what their overall phase is is
mathematical term for that but uh but uh
we don't need
it
questions all right we've gone through a
lot of stuff
um we will make it more precise the next
time when we discuss observables in
particular when we discuss what the
mathematical nature of these Sigma X's
Sigma y's and sigma z's are for the
moment we just specified them sort of by
experiment you hold your apparatus this
way and you measure something called
Sigma X you hold it that way you measure
something called Sigma Y and we use some
symmetries namely the equivalents of
different directions of
space uh to guide us into
finding um
expressions for the
various
physical vectors describing different
orientations of the spin but we haven't
been very rigorous about it and there's
been no I have made no pretense of
really a mathematical clear derivation
of these things sort of seat of the
pants guessing to a large extent the
next time we will make some rigorous uh
postulates
about what these things really
mean and their
relationship these things and these
things and what the relationship between
them is the vectors and the things that
you
measure these are the states but these
are the things you measure about them
and the question is what's the
connection between
them okay any more questions about this
the are these lectures tracking the
content in the sequence of those in the
web I imagine they are but I don't
remember but there's only one way that I
know how to think about quantum
mechanics so I bet they
are and you know if you're sitting
through this for the third time that's
your
problem believe me I'm sting through it
through the
uh yeah that pH factor that we can
ignore yes the answer is yes I think
is that phase Factor are we going to be
doing anything with that going be
looking at that at
all
well mostly we'll be saying look it it
doesn't matter all right it doesn't
matter
um the okay so let's let's talk about
the mathematics of ignoring
something yeah that's
right yeah yeah that's no that that's
true but
uh let's just talk about the mathematics
of ignoring things for a
minute all right a point is Zero
Dimensional
right a circle is onedimensional has one
parameter an angle on it but supposing I
tell you that there's no significance to
where you are on that Circle there's no
significance whatever all points on that
Circle are equivalent to every other
point then you might say well for all
interesting questions the circle is just
a point if you can ignore where you are
on the
circle then uh there's only one point on
the circle you're either on the circle
well if you're on the circle you're on
the circle there's one point you can uh
say the same
thing about let's see another example
what's another
example
um well let's take this
example if you have
a well what is a complex number a
complex number is a point on the plane
but if for some reason the angle of
where you are on the plane doesn't
matter then the only thing that's
interesting is the
distance but now supposing you have two
complex numbers and all I tell you is
that when you have two complex numbers
the thing which doesn't
matter is the sum of their
phases the sum of their phases the sum
of their
angles then there is still one angle
left over which may be important the
difference of the angles so if I have
two complex
numbers and I tell you for reasons that
I haven't specified yet that the overall
phase which can just be thought of as
the SU sum of the phase angles if the
sum of the phase angles for whatever
reason plays no role in the physics of
the situation there is still the
difference of angles there that's
exactly what the case is the sum of the
angles F the you know of the complex
numbers that go into these entries here
is of no physical
significance we counted up four real
parameters for two complex numbers the
overall magnitude of it doesn't count
because we divide that out that removes
one of them and then the sum of the
angles doesn't count for whatever reason
that removes another one that leaves you
with two uh with two real
numbers and that's in correspondence
with the two real numbers that it takes
to pick a direction in
space so there's a lot of subtlety but
nothing very difficult the mathematics
is really easy the mathematics of
quantum mechanics is easy easier than
the mathematics of classical
physics uh 2 by two matrices uh is very
simple mathematics is easier it's
unfamiliar yeah there's something that's
always been vely unsettling which I
think get at the heart of all this of
the the idea that the up and down are
along a single axis one pointing this
way and one pointing that way but
they're or somehow
too orthogonal doesn't mean
perpendicular in threedimensional space
it means physically
distinguishable it means unambiguously
distinguishable left and right are not
physically distinguishable uniquely from
up and down why because if you have a
thing oriented along
left and you measure up or down you
might get
up so you we think of I have think of
two orthogonal axises being two
independent variables that you could
vary independently yes that's right so
here you can vary
independently the probability for up and
down of course they have to add up to
one right they have to add up to one but
ignoring the question of whether they
add up to one you have the freedom to
independently vary the coefficient in
terms of you and the coefficient in
terms of
D now the fact that they have to add up
to one is is another
fact yeah don't confuse orthogonality in
the space of states with orthogonality
in uh in
um in three-dimensional space the analog
idea in Phase
space
um or in the configuration space of a
classical
system orthogonality of two probability
distributions let's think of let's
suppose you have phase space or the
configuration space of some classical
system here's a phase Space X and P and
I give you a probability distribution a
simple probability distribution might be
zero everywhere except in some
patch where the probability is
uniform okay
the analog of
orthogonality between of two distinct
probability distributions is that they
don't
overlap that they're not
overlapping uh that there's no
ambiguity
and that's the analog of
orthogonality up and down don't overlap
if you're up you're not down and if
you're down you're not
up
right now if you think about there is a
situation in which
orthogonality is the same in space and
in the space of States it's the
polarization of
photons the polarization of photons is a
little bit different and uh I didn't
want to get into it because it's more
complicated
um but
uh right it would have been better if
there was a different word for
perpendicularity in space and
orthogonality in space of
States different
concept I mean it's very much what's
going on here that being oriented along
right
um yeah
can I do an experiment which can
distinguish between a spin pointing up
and a spin pointing
down yes you can bring your apparatus
over to it detect it and if it's up
It'll point one if it's down It'll point
minus one or it'll give a minus one can
you use that apparatus to tell you
uniquely the difference between a spin
pointing along the xaxis and a spin
pointing along the z a AIS what would
you do to tell the
difference what would you
measure no matter what you measure it's
not going to uniquely tell you the
difference if you measure Sigma Z and
you get + one that doesn't tell you
anything about Sigma X it
doesn't you could have gotten Sigma zal
+ one because it was pointing along the
z-axis and you got it with certainty one
or it was pointing along the x-axis and
with probability a half you got it
pointing up there's no way to tell
there's no way to tell by a single well-
defined experiment whether the spin was
pointing let's say up or
R what if you measure if a photon comes
off or
not uh with one experiment either a
photon will or won't come off and um and
from that you cannot tell you teely
whether it was
uh no you can't tell from that it's
exactly the same as measuring the spin
if you get up in your measurement it
does not tell you whether it was
initially up or it was initially
sideways and with probability a half you
got
up okay so there's no unique single
experiment you can do to distinguish
this from this there is an experiment
that you can do to distinguish this from
this that's what makes up and down
orthogonal but down and left not
orthogonal they
overlap they overlap and in fact the
probability that if you are in left that
you measure down when you measure Sigma
Z that's a measure of the overlap
between
them right the overlap which means in
technical language it's an
orthogonal so backtrack to the hierarchy
thing originally you said we didn't know
it was programmed up Z but if we
measured up Z and got up we didn't have
to measure anything else say if the qu
we're trying to do is confirm the
proposition the spin is up or the spin
or the X comp the Z component of spin is
up or the X component of spin is
up we want to confirm that that's a
single proposition it's not two
propositions it's a single the spin is
up
or the spin is uh the spin is up along Z
or it's up along X that's a single
proposition if the first detection
measures the spin up along the z-axis
were
finished
right and and and then since the setup
was set up beforehand we know that in
that case we would get the right answer
okay okay I think would it be fair to
yeah would it be fair to summarize that
point as saying that propositions are
not
commutative uh
yeah yeah propos yeah I mean actually
propositions technically correspond to
uh projection operators and projection
operators are not
commutative that it would be proper to
some sum I don't know if that summarizes
everything about it but that certainly
summarizes part of that point you
know depends on which order you uh yeah
so you've cautioned us about trying to
visualize okay but so it is the sigma
along the z-axis or along the x- axis
isn't isn't that a visualization that it
is it is it is it is it is it is it is
it is explain why doesn't sense
well
yeah yeah yeah no it is it is a
visualization
um do keep in mind though this
interesting fact that on the
average the spins if you measure many of
them many many many of them the average
values do
behave like uh like components of a
little Vector in particular
if you take a large number of these
spins and you make sure that they're all
pointing upward and then you measure
some oblique component of
them with your apparatus being
tilted then the average that you'll get
for the oblique component will just be
the projection of the upright Vector
onto the oblique Direction exactly as if
you were measuring the component of a
vector so the um the upshot is if you
have a large number of
them in many cases you can visualize
with classical physics after all that's
what classical physics is classical
physics is to a large
extent the
approximation of systems which consist
of many many parts uh which all behave
uh simultaneously the same way
so I'll try one more question uh is
there any looking at the properties of
the model you described is there any
relation between that and the notion of
gauging
variance I
suppose I suppose there is you'd have to
be more specific than
that uh gaug inv variance does have to
do with these phase factors here yeah it
does have to do with them but
um it does have to do with them but I we
can't get into that right
now I say one thing that that I find
myself getting confused about but I
think I see it now is that we're calling
a measurement and the tendency is to
think of a measurement in the classical
sense like here comes a say a particle
or we're going to measure some property
but it's not like that because we can't
really say
what the value was before we did the
measurement we can only say what it is
after we do the meas but then once we
measure it we can measure it again and
the same thing again and there will be
consistency I mean we we put it in a
certain State and we know what that
state
is and if if we do the same exact
preparation over and over and over again
we get this
distribution that's right you can't uh
you can't always think that a system has
a property and it's just your job to
find out what it is
yeah for more please visit us at
stanford.edu